so welcome welcome back Chris thanks guy
as we unite in band on my screen and our
script no wait a minute I thought we
covered this on my screen
oh right right sorry I got momentarily
disoriented yeah so it's been it's been
a while since we returned to Plato and I
think mostly because on some level
you've been too busy doing Plato great
like like yeah because we so often we
just get on and it we just start into a
conversation but this is always kind of
the spirit of it you know in a certain
sense so it's just nice to get back to
it and note yeah exactly
incomplete we always we always set out
we always set out with the intention of
reading right but then we we become we
become very distracted yeah and we
follow things where they may which i
think is right I think it's right that
we do that
yeah but it's also nice to return yeah
so speaking of returning let's so we're
on page 590 in the Alka beatty's chapter
and I'll I there's a link I'll include
to this to this collected volumes and I
will start as Alka babies now cab ad
says you're right great thanks end of
discussion
after all that's what matters right
that's right okay if being self
controlled is knowing yourself then
their skills don't make any of them self
controlled I don't think so that's why
we consider these skills to be beneath
us and not suitable for a gentleman to
learn you're quite right again further
furthermore if someone takes care of his
body then isn't he caring for something
that belongs to him and not for himself
seems likely and isn't someone who takes
care of his wealth carrying neither for
himself nor for what belongs to him but
for something even further away and I
agree so the money earner is not in fact
doing his own work right again
now if there was someone who loved
alcibiades body
it wouldn't be loving Alcibiades only
something that belonged to our bodies
that's right but someone who loved you
would love your soul by our argument I
think he'd have to wouldn't somebody
wouldn't someone who loves your body go
off and leave you when your beauty is no
longer in full bloom obviously but
someone who loves your soul will not
leave you as long as you're making
progress that's probably right well I'm
the one who won't leave you I'm the one
who will stay with you now that your
body has lost its bloom and everyone
else has gone away
all right let's pause I just wanna pause
right there a backhanded compliment if
there ever was one
it's not a compliment at all but a
backhanded consolation I supposed
totally so this kind of get I think this
is this is this points to something like
this is this socrates here's a moment
where Socrates is revealing what he's
doing right like where he discloses
himself and he points to like what he's
doing and you kind of get this sense of
all of these circles that he's been
running him through and kind of torching
alka biteys right over and over and over
and over again he's like it seems like
this is one of those moments where he's
like I love your soul I'm not just gonna
like use you until use you and throw you
away like I'm actually doing something
this whole time yes right yes beautiful
moment he's just made sense of
everything that has come before yeah
yeah it also says characterized the
relationship yeah way that now makes
sense of its multitude of interactions
can now be understood in light of the
relationship he has just described that
the fact that he is he has
he has committed himself to the soul of
Alcibiades is precisely this is is is
that by which to understand all of the
interactions that have come hither to
this moment right
there's the here that there's the
heretic part you're kind of like yeah I
just have that sense of when he said
that it's like yeah basically I won't
leave you I'm the one who will stay with
you right and it's like Amy says I will
stay with you he's also calling to
everything that just happened in that
conversation it just pulled that whole
circle around right it's right that's
interesting yeah that's right that's
right
okay that's right I'll go on and find
out what alka baby says I'm glad you are
Socrates and I hope you'd never leave me
and you must try to be as attractive as
possible
so what I say to all my friends too I
I'll certainly try so this is your
situation you al Spidey son of clintus
have no lovers and never have had any it
seems except for one only and here's
your darling Socrates son of Safran
discus and Finnerty true remember when I
first spoke to you you said that you
were just about to say something you
wanted to ask me why I was the only one
who hadn't given up on you that's right
well this is the reason I was your only
lover
the others were only lovers of what you
had while your possessions are passing
their prime you are just beginning to
bloom I shall never forsake you now
never unless the Athenian people make
you corrupt and ugly and that is my
greatest fear that a love of the common
people might corrupt you for many
Athenian gentlemen have suffered that
fate already the people of great hearted
erect theists
look attractive on the outside but you
need to scrutinize them in their
nakedness
so take the precaution I urge what
precaution get in training first my dear
friend and learn what you need to know
before entering politics that will give
you an antidote against the terrible
dangers people really listen to him
you know 2000 years ago as you are now
demonstrating so this right so right
here okay let let I kind of want I want
I kind of want to like there's something
really big right there right of well one
he's making a distinction right so he's
pulling in the common right and that
it's basically and if you go to the way
in the common they can make you ugly
right but I'm seeing what is most
beautiful in you yet unbloomed and and
it's gonna take something beautiful and
you that to the training to be able to
bloom it right yes that's right right
that's right and then as a primer before
entering into a political arena this is
very significant to right because
ultimately what he is trying to dispose
in this relationship the love and
attention and caring for the soul that
he's trying to provoke our bodies into
should prefigure any foray into
something less than ultimate something
that engages Alcibiades at the level of
his possessions at the level of his
identity that is subordinate to the
identity of the soul that Socrates is
trying to stoke and so he's prefiguring
the boundaries of the arena in which
Alcibiades will enter into play in order
that Alcibiades does not mistake
the arena and the game he's playing for
anything more ultimate than it is right
so it's almost like he's giving him a
view of the landscape into which he will
now venture so that he doesn't lose
himself within it when he enters it so
that he can be Ricky can retrieve and be
retrieved from it
properly he's warning ya it's almost
like Socrates is warning him and
initiating him in a non idolatry
precisely like and on some level he's
got to give up everything that's common
right to realize maybe what can't even
be seen on some level right trying to be
trained and he's got to be trained in
the ability to do that because if not
then the agent arena right relationships
itself process won't it'll be all
participation with no individuation
right or or the individual the
individual will be an inauthentic one
closed in the house like in the close of
the Commons just given by what they want
so there's a kind in the sense of like
participation the tillich sense of the
participation and the individuation and
so Socrates saying hold that tension in
fact you're not ready for that tension
yeah go and like find something that you
can't actually grasp right that you
don't go into images basically sorry huh
that's right that's right that's right
so that this his identity relation
always remains straddling between what's
inside of the boundaries of the
politicking of the game he's played and
part of it always remains outside the
bar right it's like a transforming
exercise understanding that his the
composure of his identity has to
straddle the in the interior and
exterior boundaries of the frame rather
than to be enveloped by them entirely
and so Socrates sort of assess is
maintaining attention of his perspective
maintaining a presence of his
perspective outside the boundaries and
in then in the tension between what is
inside and what is outside maintaining a
tether on his soul and that's it sounds
like Socrates in some ways loss is
loving that part in him he's loving it
right and he's
saying that's the most beautiful thing
and I think what what I'm getting is the
sense of and maybe and maybe if we like
look at what the soul is and this it
sounds like it's that which is in some
straddling really it's connected to the
continuity of all those things so if
like Socrates loves his soul right
basically he's saying I'm gonna like as
that blossoms
it'll blossom in like right relationship
as you're describing here that thing
that's parents that's right that's right
yeah yeah exactly exactly it's a way of
saying what Socrates loves the more of
him that's now dawning into
consciousness as a consequence of having
lost all of those all of those
frivolities by which he constituted his
identity before the fact of this
dialogue and he's also saying like it by
the way since I'm taking one for the
team trying to look good to try to stay
pretty it's not gonna matter ultimately
yeah you bet yeah you bet you bet okay
so this I think you're right Socrates is
that is that where we are yes it is yeah
I think you're right Socrates but try to
explain how exactly we should cultivate
ourselves well we've made one step
forward anyway we've pretty well agreed
what we are we were afraid that we might
make a mistake about that and
unwittingly cultivate something other
than ourselves that which I think which
I think is that the right that returns
us to the point right which is that he
wants to be sure that whatever is being
cultivated here is is is is the self
that can no itself has more yeah then
what it then what is prescribed of it by
the particular parameters
of its exercise in the confines of
athenian activity rehearsais right right
that's the self that must be regathered
right and and throughout this whole
thing he's exemplified how you could
unwittingly cultivate something other
than ourselves that's right right that
you could be it's filled with
self-deception right it's possible to
try to or think you are and then the
very thing that's trying keeps you from
noticing that you aren't at all right
huh and alka by Jesus is the same thing
that's right that's right and the next
step is that we have to cultivate our
soul and look to that obviously and let
others take care of our bodies and our
property quite so now how can we get the
clearest knowledge of our soul if we
knew that we'd probably know ourselves
as well by the guards that admirable
Delphic inscription we just mentioned
didn't we understand it what's the point
of bringing that up again Socrates I'll
tell you what I suspect to that
inscription means and what advice it's
giving us there may not be many examples
of it except the case of sight what do
you mean by that you think about it too
if the inscription took our eyes to be
men and advised them see thyself how
would we understand such advice
shouldn't the eye be looking at
something in which you could see itself
obviously then let's think of something
that allows us to see both it and
ourselves when we look at it all right
here's where the Socratic self-knowledge
starts to become really definitional
really definitional here yeah yeah
obviously Socrates you mean mirrors and
that sort of thing quite right and isn't
there something like that in the eye
which we see with
certainly I'm sure you've noticed that
when a man looks into an eye his face
appears in it like in a mirror we call
this the pupil 4 it's a sort of
miniature of the man who's looking
you're right then and I will see itself
is if it observes an eye and looks at
the best part of it the part which it
can see see so it seems but it won't see
itself if it looks at anything else in a
man or anything else at all unless it's
similar to the eye you're right so if an
eye is to see itself it must look at an
eye and at that region of it in which
the good activity of an eye actually
occurs and this I presume is seeing
that's right
then if the sole of IDs is to know
itself it must look at a soul and
especially at that region in which what
makes a good soul sorry let me take this
again then if a soul then if the soul
also by D's is to know itself it must
look at a soul and especially at that
region in which what makes a soul good
wisdom occurs and that anything else
which is similar to it ok so what I read
that that line could very well be I
think that mean that's a that's as good
a definition for D logos as there is
yeah yeah let's read write that in mind
right then I mean this entire sequence
but even just that line yeah and if the
soul Alcibiades is to know itself it
must look at a soul and especially at
that region in which what makes a soul
good wisdom occurs and at anything else
which is similar to it it must like it
lykan to it yeah and witness itself
emerging in the reflection of what is
good right right Italy known by it
totally even with even the thing about
like it's like there's something like
that's really shows this way in which
wisdom is not possessive all right but
it's in the relational
responsiveness of looking at at us like
looking at that which you see it and you
see yourself transparent to themselves
at the same time right yes yes that's
right that's sort of like that's right
it's a way of it's a way of in seeing
you being disclosed in me I am
simultaneously disclosed to you and to
myself right yes right that's right and
that's why that's why I think of it I
mean the word transparent it comes up
now and again when we talk about this
but I think a bit more that's why we
we've talked about this before I think
of it more as more as more of the
translucency because you're both you're
both seeing the you're both seeing the
sight organ and you're seeing by means
of the site organ simultaneously all
right and that's why you're both I mean
that's why they did the combined
integration and differentiation come
from well cisely because of that trend
it's loose yeah yeah you're not you're
not simply seeing through to yourself
you're seeing what is seeing in addition
to be holding it's beholden right and I
think that's right that's what's
significant here I also I mean the the
the top of the page when Socrates says
you know I'm sure you've noticed that
when a man looks into an eye his face
appears in it like a mirror we call this
the pupil I mean I can't help but enjoy
the double meaning of people - yes yeah
absolutely and then yeah that
perspective speaks a whole lot unto
itself right and in a certain sense
Socrates is bringing him up to peer yeah
that's right
right it's writing peers that's right
right that's right that's right well the
people comes to peer yeah yeah
and I'll Kabaddi says and I agree with
you Socrates
I think I've lost the plot here guy
where are we again
oh we're like yeah so you just wrote oh
I got it I got it yeah I got it can we
say that there is anything about the
soul which is more divine than we're
knowing and understanding take place
sorry I missed I missed a word there can
we say that that there is anything about
the soul which is more divine than that
where knowing and understanding take
place no we can't then that region in it
resembles the divine and someone who
looked at that and grasped everything
divine vision and understanding would
have the best grasp of himself as well
so it seems but we agreed that knowing
oneself was the same as being self
controlled certainly so if we don't know
ourselves and weren't self controlled
would we be able to know which of the
things that belong to us were good in
which were bad how could we know that
Socrates no I suppose it would seem
impossible to you to know that what
belonged to know that what belongs to
Alcibiades belongs to him without
knowing us why he's quite impossible I'm
sure and similarly we couldn't know it
belongs to us
sorry and similarly we couldn't know
that what belongs to us belongs to us
without knowing ourselves how could we
and if we didn't even know what belongs
to us how could we possibly know what
belongs to our belongings
we couldn't then it wasn't quite right
to agree as we did a few minutes ago
that some people know what belongs to
them without knowing themselves while
others know what belongs to their
belongings it seems that it's the job of
one man and one skill to know all these
things himself his belongings and his
belongings belongings that seemed likely
and it follows that anyone who doesn't
know his own belongings probably won't
know other people's belongings either
quite so and if he doesn't know other
people's belongings nor will he know it
belongs to the city he couldn't so
man couldn't become a statesman of
course not nor could he even manage a
household estate of course not
nor indeed will he know what he's doing
certainly not and if he doesn't know
what he's doing
won't he make mistakes certainly since
he make mistakes won't he conduct
himself badly both publicly and
privately of course since he conducts
himself badly won't he be a failure
absolutely what about the people he's
working for they will I'm sorry they
will be too then it's impossible for
anyone to prosper unless he is self
controlled and good impossible so it's
the bad men who are failures absolutely
and so the way to avoid being a failure
is not by getting rich but by being self
controlled apparently so it's not walls
or warships you just make sure you're on
the right page there yes so it's not so
it's not walls or warships or shipyards
that cities need I'll survive Iza fare
to prosper nor is it numbers or size
without virtue definitely so if you want
to manage the city's business properly
and well you must impart virtue to the
citizens is virtue of course is it
possible to impart something you haven't
got
how could you then you or anyone else
who is to be ruler and trusty not only
of himself in his private business but
also the city in the city's business
must first acquire virtue himself you're
right so what you need to get for
yourself and for the city isn't
political power nor the authority to do
what you like what you need is justice
and self-control apparently because my
dear Alcibiades when an individual or a
city with no intelligence is at liberty
to do what he or it wants what do you
think a likely result will be for
example if he's sick and has the power
to do whatever he likes without any
medical insight but with such a
dictators power that nobody criticizes
what's gonna happen isn't it likely his
health will be ruined
you're right and in a ship if someone
were free to do what you liked but was
completely lacking an insight and skill
and navigation don't you see what would
happen to him and his fellow sailors I
do indeed they would all die
likewise anis likewise of a city or any
ruler or administrator is lacking in
virtue then bad conduct will result it
must well then my good Alcibiades a few
are to prosper it isn't supreme power
you need to get for yourself or the city
but virtue you're right but before one
acquires virtue it's better to be ruled
by somebody superior than to rule the
supplies to man as well as to boys so it
seems and isn't what is better
also more admirable yes and isn't what
is more admirable more appropriate of
course so it's appropriate for a bad man
to be a slave since it's better yes and
vice is appropriate for a slave
apparently and virtue is appropriate for
a free man yes
well my friend shouldn't we avoid
whatever is appropriate for slaves yes
as much as possible
Socrates can you see what condition
you're now in is it appropriate for a
free man or not I think I see only too
clearly then do you know how to escape
from your present state let's not call a
handsome young man by that name I do how
it's up to you Socrates that's not well
said I'll serve IDs well what should I
say
that it's up to God then that's what I
say and furthermore I say this as well
we're probably going to change roles
Socrates I'll be playing yours and
you'll be playing mine for from this day
forward I will never fail to attend to
attend on you and you will always have
me as your attendant and my love for you
my excellent friend will be just like a
stork after hatching a winged love in
you it will be cared for by it in return
yes that's right I'll start to cultivate
justice in myself right now I should
like to believe that you will preserve
sorry I would like to believe that you
will persevere but I'm afraid not
because I just trust your nature but
because I know how powerful the city is
and the fruit it might get the better of
both me and you Wow well I think just
right in those in that part like this
last part that we read I think I'm
starting to get the the beginnings of
the wisdom of the order actually hmm
right because it just seems to set so
many things up right you mean the
reading order yeah the reading yeah yeah
right yeah yeah yeah yeah well because
it isn't it yeah isn't it telling that
it begins or sorry rather concludes with
a with an open-ended proposal yeah yeah
not a proposition but a probe by John
makes this distinction often right I
think it's a good distinction the
proposal that's the deed and the
proposition that's the speech being it
ends with the proposal a proposal it's a
covenant 'el proposal almost a mutual
commitment
yeah and and also by the very end he's
like any seriously saying and we're
probably not gonna stay in a veil yeah
which like says to like speak it places
in the right aspirational spec place
right right like that's right like it
mostly admits of like the whoa
ones who would do this aren't the ones
talking right now right they're the ones
that could be yeah yeah that's right
that's right so interesting how it just
kept it's like it both kept tithing
tightening up the circle kept tightening
up but also pointing to more and more of
the center being everywhere right this
sense right I really got this sense of
the dot that the dialectic between
especially at the end whereas like
between the thing that Socrates loves in
Alcibiades right right is not the thing
is not the city right it's like no he's
got a it's the thing he's loving is the
thing that needs to be educated right to
be a self that and this is what's
interesting it to be a self that is
called by virtue right not by any the
like the not by any the mechanisms that
you can kind of normally just you know
take to be a city right but what its
gonna take to be the city is a virtue
so like that comically it opens up about
virtue there to that's right that's
right that's right and and then the the
the home that they're trying to mutually
make in virtue is held is is is held and
belonged together in virtue of their
relationship right because the dialogue
even as adventures into one proposition
or another it always returns again and
again and again right does so at the
very beginning and then again somewhere
in the middle and then again here at the
end it always returns to the the re
commitment of their file eeeh as the
thing that will anchor their
correspondence to the virtue that
they're trying to that they're trying to
invoke eight here right it's it's it's
there it's there
their affinity that draws them back into
virtue when everything else will
threaten to undermine it right right
that's the speaking it's the speaking
into one another yeah that will
recollect the presence that knows their
mutual identities in virtue of each
other right
and like Alka Betty's even says at the
very the last thing he says what was it
like he said and cultivate justice and
myself right now he said right in the
part before that where he says well then
that's what I say and furthermore I say
this as well we're probably going to
change roles right that just that sense
of presencing again it's like it's
presencing that you know who is the
character Socrates right yeah like like
there it shows like a kind of
interchangeability right of the roles of
like maybe one can be handed over to the
other right that this is something that
isn't it isn't in me it isn't in
Socrates but it's sometimes right it's
somehow Haley it's a Talos right yes
right and that just that sense of just
the calling like that the world right
withdrawals right and the it withdrawals
as the character becoming figure right
the the world exists that just that
sense I think it shows the the non yet
like this is fine it keeps the keeps
coming to me it's like it's it's on some
level you could almost look at this
dialog is Socrates completely holding up
an image and taking it down holding up a
diminution taking it down like and then
and then all the way through and they're
right the end he talks about virtue but
the virtue is like where is the virtue
right yeah yeah cuz that because that
because the Telos of their relation is
the perceptual coming into
yeah that's why it that's why it exceeds
each of their identities yeah right
that's why I mean when when now spidey
says right I believe that we might
switch roles somehow they can switch for
the prospect of them switching roles
doesn't at all undermine the prospective
friendship and its future possibility
precisely because the mutual coming into
virtue that characterizes the relation
is over and above the identities that
are disposed in there and they're in
there in there in the commitments of the
everyday I shouldn't say commitments
that's confusing things but in the in
the sort of the roles of the everyday as
they taken up with in Athenian society
right it become kind of icons yeah to
each other yeah yeah
certainly Socrates Delphi IDs and and
but but there but the reciprocity is
loaned by Socrates to the conversation
right right yes right that's the gist I
was just surprised at how much of this
is about is is really about it's like
it's about setting up idols and taking
them away yeah yeah setting up idols and
taking them away right just that sense
of what is the thing that we're calling
real and that there that that's where it
starts to get at that sense of where the
pair even in this even in the even that
the medium is language and dialogue
right what basically I think in that
it's there like the dialogue is leading
them into something that can't actually
be said right but in that role Binks I
have a feeling the roles will be
switched right and he's saying it's like
oh yeah its presence is the thing that's
like even the thing we're circling
around that's emerging it's been calling
through the conversation the whole time
that like if you try to grab it it's not
the thing but it it's the normativity
right that's right that gret like it is
granted by
in a certain sense the future right
which ends up being the origin of the
normativity right so like the origin
thing about Heidegger now like that
sense of like yeah origin always calls
from the future hmm right because it is
that sense of like in a virtue you don't
have the virtue yet you don't have it no
way that's why you're you're coming into
it you're ever coming into it you're
coming into it you're ever having into
it totally it is something that is
something you're it and that's why I
think the possessive that the the the
inversion of the possessive relationship
is very important right yeah um similar
to the idea that you don't have ideas
ideas have you right that feels kind of
adage from you and others the same thing
applies here I think that right that
you're not you're not possessed of the
virtue of the virtue you are you are you
are possessed by the virtue you you
yield yourself to its possession almost
magnetically right and and that's why it
ends I think that's part of why you're
right I mean they're groping there
they're there they're circling around
the something that is withdrawing from
them as they Center on it what it's
that's why this ends that's somewhat
enigmatic aliy with a with a with a with
a profession to continue groping with a
profession to continual to continue to
Center on that which cannot be centered
on nice nice groping you it with you my
friend Gregor open remember stay
attractive that's why I have my shirt
you know a checkered shirt I know this
is a lot of fun
I always is it always this so we've
actually finished a dialogue hooray for
outs I really did we took our time but
that's okay it should be savored should
be safe really so we'll move on to
another one next time open a whole new
a whole new journey that will conclude
with the with the commitment to continue
groping absolutely have my friend you
have a good weekend
you too talk to you soon back okay bye